# Susanth Guru

### Data Engineer Kumbakonam, Tamilnadu, India

L+91 9500980912 

Susanth.guru.29@gmail.com III linkedin.com/in/susanthguru 

G github.com/susanth-g

#### **About**

Having 6 years of experience in documenting, designing and implementing solutions for problems of multiple usecases by analysing technologies that fit. I also have hands on experience with multiple technologies like Hadoop, HIVE, Hbase, Spark, Cloudera, GCP and Kafka to complete data ingestion pipe lines and provision of ingested data to the product user interface.

## Work Experience

Paypal ☑ Feb 2022 - Present

Data Engineer Chennai, Tamil Nadu

- Designed and implemented solutions based on Spark Streaming with Pubsub and Bigquery for creating data ingestion pipelines.
   Developed Bash scripts, SQL scripts, pySpark and Python scripts to move or recover data from multiple sources such as log files,
- JSON files and HIVE parquet files.

CanGo Networks Pvt Ltd 🖸 Nov 2019 - Feb 2022

Lead Big Data Developer

- Designed and implemented solutions based on core JAVA for CoreServices and SpringBoot for APIs.
- Developed spark based and multithreaded performant oriented applications based on JAVA to collect and parse data from various data sources such as FTP, Command output from SSH Session, messaging queues like Kafka and Pubsub.

### National Payments Corporation of India 🖸

Associate Enterprise Architect

Jul 2017 - Nov 2019

Chennai, Tamil Nadu

Chennai, Tamil Nadu

- Designed and implemented solutions based on HIVE and HBASE, Apache NIFI and Apache Phoenix.
- **Developed utility jars** to help operations team for scheduled daily reports which reduced the effort and time to generate reports manually everyday.

## **Technical Skills**

Languages and Scripts: Java 8, Spring Boot, SQL, Arango QL, Shell Script, Python

DataBase Technologies (SQL): MySQL, Postgres, HIVE, Impala

DataBase Technologies (NoSQL): HBase, ArangoDB, Elastic Search

Cloud Technologies: GCP [ BigQuery, PubSub, CloudStorage, CloudSQL, DataProc, Kubernetes ], AWS [ S3 Bucket ]

Big Data Technologies: Hadoop, Apache Spark, Apache NIFI, Spark SQL, Cloudera

Developer Tools: VS Code, Eclipse, SublimeText 4, NP++, StarUML, draw.io

Terminal Tools: bash, tmux, less, vim, htop, top

Other Technologies/Framework: Linux, Git, SVN, JUnit, Microservices, Rserve, REST API, Kubernetes, Docker, RASA ChatBot

### **Projects**

Pipe Line for BQ Data Population and Report Generation | Python, JAVA, Bigquery, Spark, Spark-UDF, PGP Enc-Dec, SFTP, Airflow Role: Data Engineer

- Developed **python** based framework **modules** as pipeline to **populate BQ tables** using queries from a file
- Developed JAVA based Spark App to Deserialize, Encrypt or Decrypt columns of data
- Developed Spark UDFs to Deserialize and convert the deserialized data to columns of a DF and then store to BQ table
- Developed BQ Export Script to download large data (~2B records 15 cols atleast 8char length) to local disk as single CSV for reports
- Developed Email Scripts to convert BQ tables to multiple HTML tables grouped on a column
- Developed scripts to PGP encrypt or decrypt complete report file before sending to destination SFTP
- Developed modules to push and pull reports or input files from SFTP directories

Cloud Migration | Spark Streaming, Pubsub, Bigquery, Dataproc, SQL, JAVA, Python, HIVE

Role: Data Engineer

- Developed a JAVA based spark streaming JAR with editable config file to fetch data from Pubsub then transform, validate and push into BQ tables.
- Recovered lost data in HIVE by regenerating data from raw log files by developing a python script, then read and pushed the data
  to HIVE using Spark and HQL.

NIMS - Network Inventory Management System | Core JAVA, JAVA Future, Jsch Library, ArangoDB

Role: Lead and Developer

- Led a small team of UI and API developers.
- Designed and Implemented the complete Data collection service using core JAVA to fetch and parse data from more than 24000 devices using SSH protocol for different vendors on daily basis.

#### MAXIS - OptiGo Al Product | JAVA Spark, Hive, Impala, MySQL, SpringBoot

Role: Developer

- Implemented a **Data parser** to populate performance data from csv or xml files using **Spark SQL** into Hive database by applying pivots and transformations over dataframes as required. Optimised Spark SQL performance with persistence.
- Designed and implemented a KQI calculator using spark SQL to re-aggregate performance data based on configurations to calculate KQI and push to Hive tables in a scheduled time interval.
- Developed CRUD API using SpringBoot to configure KQI from UI.
- Worked closely with Datascience team to invoke R code from JAVA Spring Boot with RServe.

#### Transaction Enquiry System - NPCI UPI, NACH | Java HTTP Servlet, Apache NIFI, Hbase, Sqoop

Role: Developer

- Designed and implemented a data ingestion pipeline using **sqoop** to fetch daily data from postgres and populate into Hive. Then using **Apache NIFI** to fetch transaction data and form rowkey based on the data, then push to Hbase.
- Implemented APIs using JAVA HTTP Servlet to fetch data from Hbase using Apache Phoenix JDBC connection.
- Developed a scheduled report generation JAR to generate reports which reduced the time to generate manual reports but enabled operations to verify or analyse the data.

#### **Publication**

Emulation of IoT Gateway 🖸

Emulation of IoT gateway for connecting sensor nodes in heterogenous ICCCSP - Research Gate

Emulation of IoT gateway for connecting sensor nodes in heterogenous networks within lab environments.

Education

SSN, Anna university Affil. 🗗 Jun 2015 - Jun 2017

Master of Engineering (M.E.,) in Computer Science

JJCET, Anna university Affil. 🗗 Jun 2011 - May 2015

Chennai, Tamil Nadu

Trichy, Tamil Nadu

Bachelor of Engineering (B.E.,) in Computer Science

Languages

Tamil - Native, English - Fluent